hey everyone happy new years we're gonna
嘿，大家新年快乐，我们要谈论的是一种称为
be talking about a data type called
enums I will explain how to define an
枚举我将解释如何定义枚举，并向您展示如何使用它。
enum and show you how it is used imagine
that I have an online bookstore and
我有一家在线书店，并且客户以其所有者的身份订购一本书
customer orders a book as the owner of
the bookstore there are several things
书店里有几件事情我需要在发货之前做
that I need to do before shipping out
the books like waiting for payments to
诸如等待付款完成和为订单准备订单之类的书
finalize and preparing the order for
shipment so when the order is created by
装运，因此当客户创建订单时，订单状态为
a customer the status of the order is
pending
收到付款后，我将待处理
once I've received the payment I'm gonna
ship the book so the status of the order
寄出书籍，因此订单状态将在寄出后立即寄出
will be shipped once the shipment
arrives at the customer he can either
到达客户时，他可以接受或拒绝它，原因如下
accept it or reject it for reasons like
damage during shipment or I sent the
运输过程中损坏或我寄错书本，客户可以取消
wrong books and the customer can cancel
order while the status of the order is
订单，而订单状态仍处于待处理状态，则他们不应该
still pending and they shouldn't be able
to cancel their order once the order is
要在订单发货后取消订单，我们可以为
shipped we can model the
state-transition using a data type
使用名为enum的数据类型进行状态转换来定义您的枚举类型
called enum to define an enum type you
start with the keyword enum followed by
以关键字enum开头，后跟我们要称为的类型的名称
the name of the type we're gonna call
this type status inside the braces were
大括号内的这种类型的状态将列出所有可能的状态
gonna list out all possible status of
the order the statuses that we mentioned
订单我们之前提到的状态或待发货状态已接受或
earlier or pending shipped accepted or
rejected and finally cancelled we're
拒绝并最终取消，我们将订单状态存储在公共场所
gonna store the order status in a public
state variable and the way you do it is
状态变量和您的操作方式是这样的
like this
[Music]
[音乐]在这里我声明的是
here I'm declaring that the type of the
data is status and it's a public state
数据是状态，它是一个公共状态变量，并存储在名称中
variable and it's stored in a name
called status notice that the status
称为状态通知，状态数据类型不是内置数据类型
data type is not a built-in data type it
is a data type that we declared here now
是一种数据类型，我们现在在此处声明该枚举类型的默认值将为
the default value for the enum type will
be the first element in the definition
是枚举定义中的第一个元素，因此在这种情况下，尚待处理的是
of the enum so in this case pending is
the first term and defined in einem so
第一项，并在einem中定义，因此我们的公共状态变量为
our public state variable will be
initialized to pending once I shift
我想将状态更新为时将订单初始化为待处理
order I want to update the status to
shift so we're gonna create your
移动，以便我们创建您要执行的功能
function to do that we're gonna create
your public function called ship and the
您的公共功能称为ship，而您更新状态的方式就像
way you will update the status is like
this and we only want to update the
这并且我们只想在当前状态为的情况下将状态更新为shift
status to shift if the current status is
still pending and the way you would do
仍然悬而未决，您要做的方式就是这样，我们将要求
it is like this we're gonna require that
the status is still pending so this
状态仍处于待处理状态，因此此功能会将状态更新为班次
function will update the status to shift
only if the current status is still
仅在订单发货后当前状态仍处于待处理状态时
pending once the order has been shipped
and the customer receives the delivery
并且客户收到交货后，客户可以接受
the customer can either accept the
delivery or rejected so we're going to
交付或拒绝，所以我们将创建两个公共职能，除了
create two public functions except
delivery and reject delivery
交货和拒绝交货
now both of these function will have a
现在这两个功能在这里都具有与此功能相似的逻辑，因此
similar logic to this function here so
we're gonna copy the code and modify it
我们将复制代码并对其进行一些修改，我们只需要此功能
a little bit we only want this function
to be called by the customer if the
如果当前状态为出厂且为当前状态，则由客户调用
current status is shipped and if it is
then we're gonna update the status to
那么我们将更新状态以接受它，而我们只想拒绝
accept it and we only want to reject
delivery to be called if the current
如果当前状态为出厂，则调用该交货，在这种情况下，我们将
status is shipped and in that case we're
gonna update the status to reject it
要更新状态以最终拒绝它，我们希望客户能够
finally we want the customer to be able
to cancel their order if the status of
如果订单状态仍待处理，则取消他们的订单，因此我们
the order is still pending so we're
gonna create a function called cancel
要创建一个称为取消的函数
and this function should be called if
如果状态等于待处理且处于
the status is equal to pending and in
that case we're gonna update the status
在这种情况下，我们将要更新状态以取消并覆盖所有状态
to cancel and that covers all state
transitions for the status of the order
订单状态的转换让我们编译部署合同，然后
let's compile deploy the contract and
test it out first call status and you'll
测试它的首次通话状态，您会发现自己没有待处理
notice that you don't get pending
instead you get a number zero this is
相反，您得到的数字为零，这是因为零对应于我们的第一个
because zero corresponds to our first
element in our enum so one will be
枚举中的一个元素，因此将被发送两个将被接受三个将
shipped two will be accepted three will
be rejected and four will be cancelled
被拒绝，下一个呼叫船将取消四个，您可以检查一下
next call ship and you can check that
the status is now equal to one so that
现在的状态等于1，这意味着我们当前的状态等于
means our current status is equal to
shipped and if you try to cancel a
发货，如果您尝试取消发货订单，您会注意到我们的
shipped order you'll notice that our
transaction failed this is because you
交易失败，这是因为您只能在状态为
can only call canceled if the status is
still pending
仍在等待中，因此一旦状态被发送，唯一的
so once the status is shipped the only
two function that we can call or either
我们可以调用或接受交付的两个功能
accept delivery
or reject delivery call accept delivery
或拒绝送货电话接受送货，您可以验证状态为
and you can verify that the status is
now equal to two which is equal to
现在等于2，等于已接受，如果您尝试拒绝
accepted and if you try to reject the
delivery after it's been accepted you'll
交付后，您会注意到交易将失败
notice that the transaction will fail
again this is because you can only
同样，这是因为您只能在状态为
reject the delivery if the status is to
equal to shipped now let's try
等于现在发货，让我们尝试取消订单，以便
cancelling the order so we're going to
delete this contract and redeploy a new
删除此合同并重新部署新合同
one
as before the initial status of the
与之前一样，订单的初始状态为零，等于待处理状态
order is zero which is equal to pending
next call cancel and check the status
下次通话取消并检查状态，现在状态等于4，其中
the status is now equal to four which
corresponds to the fifth element in our
对应于我们的状态枚举中的第五个元素，它等于cancel和
status enum which is equal to cancel and
once the order is canceled we won't be
订单取消后，我们将无法发货，您可以验证
able to ship it you can verify that the
transaction failed and that's because we
交易失败，这是因为我们无法塑造已经存在的订单
cannot shape an order that's been
cancelled and that's how you use enum to
已取消，这就是您使用枚举为状态转换建模的方式，即
model state transition in other words by
using enum you can control when a
使用枚举，您可以控制何时可以调用函数以及不能调用函数
function can and cannot be called well
that's all I'd offer this video thanks
这就是我要提供的所有视频，感谢您的观看，我们将在
for watching and I'll see you in the
next video
下一个视频